Guide to the Catherine Jane Personius papers, 1930-1967,
Personius, Catherine Jane papers
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Catherine Jane Personius papers, 1930-1967, 1940-1967 (bulk).
23-14-979
Catherine Jane, Personius 1904-
5 cubic ft.
Publications, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Includes printed and photocopied material, and other papers relating to Personius' work.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Professor of food and nutrition, Cornell University.
Catherine Personius graduated from Elmira College in 1925 with a degree in home economics and chemistry, subsequently joining the staff as foods instructor. In 1928, she completed her M.A. at Teacher's College, Columbia University and in 1937 her Ph.D. from Cornell, joining the faculty as an assistant professor that same year. From 1940-1943, she was an associate professor at the University of Wisconsin, Madison, and then returned to Cornell as professor and co-chair of the Department of Food and Nutrition and a year later as chair. In 1947, she also became Coordinator of Research for the College and Assistant Director of the Experiment Station. Personius was the first woman to be a faculty representative on the Board of Trustees where she served from 1959-1964. She retired in 1966.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Includes printed and photocopied material, and other papers relating to Personius' work as a teacher and researcher in home economics, especially relating to her field of food and nutrition and with the Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Personius, Catherine Jane,1904-; Cornell University--Faculty.; Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges.
Subjects:
Home economics.; Nutrition.; Women college teachers.; Home economists.; Nutritionists.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
SERIES LIST
Series I. Biographical Material
Series II. Course Material
Series III. Subject and Reference Files
Series IV. Cornell Committees, Events, Projects, Research
Series V. Outside Associations and Organizations
Series VI. American Home Economics Association (AHEA)
Series VII. Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges (ASULGC)
Series VIII. Northeast Region
CONTAINER LIST
- Series I. Biographical Material
  - Biographical Information, including photograph, 1937-1966 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Reprints and Manuscripts, 1938-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Course Notes - University of Wisconsin, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Talks and Papers by Personius, 1947-1961 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Talks and Papers by Personius, 1962-1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1949-1964 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence and Memos, 1955-1965 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence - Various Outside Organizations, 1959-1964 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Board of Directors - Cornell Research Foundation, 1955-1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Trip to Russia, 1959-1960 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Consulting Project - Carnegie Institute of Technology, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Oral History Project, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Oral History Transcript, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Series II. Course Material
  - Core Curriculum, 1938-1944 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Sub-Freshman Foods Questionnaire, 1938 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Food Tests, 1939 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Food and Nutrition Lab Notebook (1), 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Food and Nutrition Lab Notebook (2), 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Lectures - 1st Term, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Lectures - 2nd Term, 1938-1939 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Lectures - 1st Term, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Lectures - 2nd Term, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Lectures, 1952-1959 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Lectures and Labs, 1955-1961 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Course Material (1), 1933-1939 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Course Material (2), 1931-1939 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Course Material (3), 1934-1939 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Course Material, 1936 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Course Material (1), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Course Material (2), 1940 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Lectures - Cora Miller, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Department Curriculum Study, 1947-1949 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Food and Nutrition Course Material, 1950s (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Food and Nutrition Course Material, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Food and Nutrition - Summer Session, 1951 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Food and Nutrition - Course Material, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Flour, 1961-1963 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Food and Nutrition (FN) 314 Course Material, 1944-1967 (Box 2, Folder 3-39)
  - FN 316 Course Material, 1947-1963 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - FN 217 Course Material, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - FN 420 Seminar - Food and Nutrition, 1955-1957 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - FN Course Material, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Course Offerings Study, 1950-1955 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Undergraduate Curriculum, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- Subject and Reference Files
  - Papers Concerning Research in Home Economics, 1925-1959 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Papers Concerning Research in Home Economics, 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Talks, Papers by Various Home Economists, 1955-1960 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Talks, Papers by Various Home Economists, 1961-1966 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Food Research Workers - Biographical Information, 1947 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Encyclopedia Americana Entry, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Doctoral Programs in Home Economics, 1954-1955 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - B. T. Shaw's Statements on Redirection of Human Nutrition and Home Economics Research, 1955-1958 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Research Needs in Agriculture, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Milkoato, Milkcorno, Milkwheato - G. L. F. (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Testing Proficiency in Food Preparation, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Soy Flours in Baking, 1941 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Soy Bean Committee, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Effect of Heat on Cheese, 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Dried Egg Powder, 1942-1943 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Dried Whey in Bread, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Dairyman's League Fellowship - Nonfat Dry Milk Solids, 1945-1951 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - American Dairy Association Project - Correspondence, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Recipes Tested for NYS Historical Association, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Vegetables - Market Growers Journal, 1945-1957 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Cherry Pie, 1946 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Yale Food Study, 1946-1949 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Calcium Treatment of Tomatoes and Apples, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Borden Award - Frances Johnston Nomination, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Cornell Executive Aircraft, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 16)
- Series IV. Cornell Committees, Events, Projects, Research
  - Radio Broadcasts, 1948-1949 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Radio Broadcasts, 1950-1950 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Post-War Planning Committee, 1943-1946 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Food Preservation Committee, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - School of Nutrition - Committee and Special Reports, 1944-1945 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Graduate Students Committee, 1945 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - College Nutrition Committee, 1948 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Library Building Program, 1950 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Conference Committee on Higher Education for Women, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - 9th and 12ths Committee, 1958-1961 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Ad Hoc Committee on Patent and Trademark Policy, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Nuclear Peril Committee, 1961-1962 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Purnell Projects in Home Economics, 1924-1930 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Purnell Act - Paper by E. W. Allen, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Home Economics Research, 1930s-1940s (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Food Technology Program, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Rural Housing Project Research, 1944-1947 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - University Policy - Research, 1948-1950 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Housing Research Center at Cornell, 1950-1951 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Social Science Research Center - Cornell, 1964-1965 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  - School of Nutrition - Freezing of Pre-Cooked Foods Research, 1944 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - School of Nutrition - Frozen Food Research, 1945-1947 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - School of Nutrition - Frozen Food, Food Preservation Research Reports, 1946-1948 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Medical Consultants, 1946-1950 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Experiment Station Staff - Identification with College - Letter from A. R. Mann to Martha van Rensselaer, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Research Appointments, 1951-1953 (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Graduate Staff, 1956-1961 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Visitors from Other Countries, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  - Institute - Nutritional Status: A Critical Evaluation, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  - Conference for Home Economists Working with Low Income Families, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Series V. Outside Associations and Organizations
  - Land Grant College Association Conference Report, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Reports and Studies at Wisconsin and Cornell, 1940-1948 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - NYS Dept. of Education Committee on Food and Nutrition Curriculum, 1945-1946 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Food and Nutrition Advisory Committee - Reports, Minutes, 1951-1962 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Home Economics Research Advisory Committee - Reports, Minutes, 1955-1966 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Interregional Committee on Nutritional Status - Meeting Minutes, 1952-1959 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - NYS Home Demonstration Agents Association - Research Committee, 1957-1959 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Workshop - Administrative Management for Home Economics in the Association of Land Grant Colleges and Universities, 1953 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Workshop - Administrative Management for Home Economics, 1957 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Workshop - Home Economics in Higher Education, 1960 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Accreditation Review - University of Tennessee; University of Delaware, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - USDA Food and Human Nutrition, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - U. S. Dept. of Health, Education, and Welfare - Home Economics Curriculum Project, 1963-1967 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Capener Committee - OEO, 1965-1966 (Box 4, Folder 6)
- Series VI. American Home Economics Association (AHEA)
  - Conference - "Strengthening Home Economics Research," Sponsored by AHEA and Oregon State University, 1966 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - AHEA - Research Department - Division of Food and Nutrition, 1938-1947 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Handbook of Food Preparation - AHEA, 1942-1947 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - AHEA - Sub-Committee on Need for Home Economics Resrach at the Federal Level, 1955-1956 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - AHEA - National Research Institute for the American Home, 1956-1961 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - AHEA - Survey of Status of Publication of Home Economics Research, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Series VII. Association of State Universities and Land-Grant Colleges (ASULGC)
  - Association of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities - Research Committees, 1947-1952 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Association of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities - Research Committees, 1952-1960 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Association of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities - Research, 1948-1951 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Association of Land-Grant Colleges and Universities - Research, 1949-1956 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Financing Research Publications - Land-Grant Committee, 1953-1954 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - ASULGC - Publications, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - ASULGC - Reports of the Executive Committee, 1960s (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Centennial Committee - Anniversary of the Establishment of Land-Grant Colleges, 1960-1962 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Centennial Committee - Anniversary of the Establishment of Land-Grant Colleges, 1960-1961 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - ASULGC - Centennial Convocation Remarks, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - ASULGC - Centennial Convocation Remarks, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - ASULGC - Study of Home Economics (1), 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - ASULGC - Study of Home Economics (2), 1961-1965 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - ASULGC - Study of Home Economics, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - ASULGC - Correspondence, 1962-1963 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - ASULGC - Home Economics Division - Reports, Memos, Correspondence (1), 1964-1966 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - ASULGC - Home Economics Division - Reports, Memos, Correspondence (2), 1966-1968 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - ASULGC - Papers Given at General Session, 1963 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - ASULGC - Papers Given at Meetings of Home Economics Division, 1964 (Box 4, Folder 31)
- Series VIII. Northeast Region
  - Northeastern Home Economics Research Workers, 1937-1945 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - NE Regional Textiles an Clothing Research Project Minutes, 1952-1954 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Regional Research Proposal - Home Economics Marketing, 1956 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - NE-4 - Correspondence, 1947 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - NE-4 - Minutes, Annual Reports, Budgets, 1947-1952 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - NE-4 - Cooperative Nutritional Status Studies in NE, 1950-1954 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - NE-16 - Minutes, 1952-1956 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - NE-16 - Project Statements, Annual Reports, Budgets, Publications, 1952-1960 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - NE-19 - Annual Reports, Procedural Manual, 1954-1960 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - NE-19 - Minutes of Committee Meetings, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - NE-19 - Revised - Minutes, Memos, 1958-1962 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - NE-19 - Revised - Annual Reports, Budgets, Publications, 1958-1964 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - NE-20 - Regional Research in Housing Meetings, 1954-1957 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - NE-37 - Annual Report Budgets, Publications, 1957-1965 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - NE-37 - Memos, 1962-1963 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - NE-37 - Revised - Regional Project Statement, Policy and Procedure, 1955-1962 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - NE-37 - Revised - Minutes, 1956-1963 (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - NE-37 - Revised - Correspondence, 1960-1966 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - NE Regional Research in Housing Projects - Not Activated, 1958 (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - NE Regional Research Exploratory Studies, 1962 (Box 5, Folder 18)
  - NEM-32 - Marketing Project - Correspondence, 1957-1958 (Box 5, Folder 19)
  - NEM-32 - Minutes, Annual Reports, 1963-1966 (Box 5, Folder 20)